Guide to the Maria Mitchell Papers, 1843-2016 (bulk 1853-1889)
Vassar College Libraries Archives and Special Collections
Maria Mitchell Papers
1843-2016
1853-1889
Mitchell, Maria, 1818-1889
12 cubic feet (55 boxes, 9 microfilm reels, 1 OV folder)
Archives and Special Collections, Vassar College Libraries
Correspondence, manuscripts, research material, photographs, and glass plate negatives relating to Mitchell's work as an astronomer and member of the faculty of Vassar College.
Biographical Note
Maria Mitchell, astronomer, was born on the island of Nantucket in 1818. Through her father, William Mitchell, she became interested in astronomy and assisted him in his observatory. In the late 1830s she was appointed librarian at the Nantucket Athenaeum, using its collection to educate herself while she worked with her father in the evenings. In 1847 she discovered a new comet, named for her, and was subsequently awarded a gold medal by the King of Denmark. A year later she became the first woman elected to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences in Boston; in 1850 she was elected to the American Association for the Advancement of Science.
At the urging of Matthew Vassar, who was eager to add a woman of considerable stature to his first faculty, Maria Mitchell came to Vassar in 1865, where an observatory with a 12-inch telescope was built for her. The materials in the Vassar collection reflect her twenty-three years at Vassar, where she became one of the college's best and most well-known teachers. During this time, she continued her own research and publication. A founder of the Association for the Advancement of Women, she urged that women's ability in the sciences be recognized and that the scientific method be applied to the solution of social problems. In recognition of her breadth of outlook, Maria Mitchell was elected to the American Philosophical Society in 1869, and in 1873 was made a vice-president of the American Social Science Association. Retiring from Vassar in 1888, she went to Lynn, Massachusetts, to work in the small observatory she had built there. She died the next year of "brain disease" and was buried in Nantucket.
Scope and Content Note
These papers reflect Mitchell's professional life and include thirty-one notebooks of astronomical observations; observatory photographs; glass plate negatives; manuscripts, notes, and drawings; letters regarding the Nautical Almanac computations, 1853; notes for preparing Vassar College Astronomy Department reports, 1871-1886; and correspondence, 1861-1889, including her letters to Benson J. Lossing, Ann Eliza Morse, John H. Raymond, Mrs. John H. Raymond, Cyrus Swan, and James Monroe Taylor, and letters from James Edward Oliver, Arthur Searle, Rufus Babcock, Charles Farrar, Nathan Bishop, and Vassar College Presidents John H. Raymond and James M. Taylor. Other items include research correspondence about Mitchell, 1907-1974; excerpts from Vassar College Trustee minutes and copies of correspondence regarding the Astronomy Department, the Observatory, and Mitchell's salary, 1862-1872; publications by Mary W. Whitney, Mary King Babbitt, and others about Mitchell; and letters from Helen Wright concerning her biography of Mitchell, circa 1949.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Nantucket Maria Mitchell Association Reports and Miscellaneous Pamphlets [520.92 M695 and 520.92 M6952], Rare Book Collection, Archives and Special Collections, Vassar College Libraries.
Vassar College Astronomy Department Records, Archives and Special Collections, Vassar College Libraries.
Subject Headings
Names:
Babbitt, Mary King, 1861-1912; Whitney, Mary Watson, 1847-1921; Morse, Ann Eliza; Raymond, John H. (John Howard), 1814-1878; Raymond, Cornelia M., 1861-1952; Swan, Cyrus; Taylor, James Monroe, 1848-1916; Oliver, James Edward, 1829-1895; Searle, Arthur; Babcock, Rufus, 1798-1875; Farrar, Charles S. (Charles Samuel), 1826-1903; Bishop, Nathan, 1808-1880; Wright, Helen, 1914-1997
Organizations:
Vassar College. Board of Trustees; Vassar College. Observatory; Vassar College. Department of Astronomy; Vassar College--Faculty; Association for the Advancement of Women; American Academy of Arts and Sciences
Subjects:
Women--Education; Astronomy--Study and teaching; Astronomy--Observations; Women's colleges--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Nautical almanacs; Women college teachers; Astronomers
Document Types:
Correspondence; Drawings (visual works); Notebooks; Photographs; Wet collodion negatives
VCL Categories:
Math, Science and Medicine; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke and Laura Streett, November 2006. Updated by Mark Seidl, November 2019. Last updated by Emma Gronbeck, September 2024.
Acquisition Information
Gift of various donors.
Series List
- Series I. Correspondence, 1849-1946; [Boxes 1-5]
  Letters to Maria Mitchell
  Letters from Maria Mitchell
  Letters about Maria Mitchell
  Correspondence re: Maria Mitchell As Her Students Knew Her
  Correspondence re: Sweeper in the Sky
- Series II. Vassar College Astronomy Department, 1871-1886; [Box 6]
- Series III. Maria Mitchell's Dome Parties, 1870; [Box 6]
- Series IV. Mitchell Notes, Lecture Notes, and Notebooks, 1843-1893; [Boxes 6-13]
- Series V. Biographical Information, 1874-2007; [Box 14]
- Series VI. Biographies of Maria Mitchell, 1932, 1984; [Box 14]
- Series VII. Publications, 1796-1995; [Boxes 15-16]
- Series VIII. Oversized Material, undated; [Box 17]
- Series IX. Microfilm of Maria Mitchell Association Collection, 1831-1888; [Reels 1-9]
  The copy of this microfilm was obtained by the Vassar College Libraries from the American Philosophical Society with the permission of the Nantucket Maria Mitchell Association.
  Note regarding Reel 7, Item 64: There is no item 64.
- Series X. Glass Plate Negatives, 1871-1890; [Boxes 18-19, Negative Boxes 1-36]
  Glass plate negatives for images of Mitchell's observations of sun spots and other astronomical phenomena. Includes 808 plates in 36 boxes.
  Observers responsible for taking the negatives include both students and faculty at Vassar, all identified by surname. Faculty noted as observers include: Maria Mitchell, Priscilla Braislin, and Mary W. Whitney.
  Student observers most likely include: Helen M. Arnold (VC 1874), [Martha] Boyd (VC 1883), [Nannie] Braden (VC 1879), [Marian H.] Bradley (VC 1887), [Annie C.] Buck (VC 1886), [Harriet L.] Cady (Ex VC 1881), [Nellie H.] Canfield (VC 1887), Mary E. Case (VC 1882), Lucy Davis (VC 1885), [Elizabeth] Deming (VC 1885), [Alla W.] Foster (VC 1872), Caroline E. Furness (VC 1891), Ella Gardner (VC 1877), M. Louise Greene (VC 1891), Josephine Harrison (VC 1881), Bertha Hazard (VC 1879), E. Carol Hodge (VC 1881), Adaline L. Jenckes (VC 1887), Rose M. Kavana (VC 1891), Emily Lewi (VC 1888), Caroline G. Lingle (VC 1886), Katherine M. Lupton (VC 1873), Hannah F. Mace (VC 1890), Frances M. Macy (VC Art 1978-1979), Cornelia W. Marsh (VC Spec 1871-1873), Antonia C. Maury (VC 1887), [Margaretta] Palmer (VC 1887), M. Eva Perry (VC 1873), Louisa B. Poppenheim (VC 1889), Cornelia M. Raymond (VC 1883), Mary Augusta Scott (VC 1876), [Frances] Southworth (VC 1886), Annie T. Spalding (VC Ex 1884), [Helen] Stanton (VC 1886), Lucretia A. Stow (VC 1874), Mary Sudduth (VC 1883), Helen Tunnicliff (VC 1889), Esther Witkowsky (VC 1886), and [Laura Johnson] Wylie (VC 1877).
  Arranged chronologically.
Container List
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE, 1849-1946
  - Letters to Maria Mitchell
    - from [Stephen] M. Buckingham, 20 June 1871; (MS) (Folder 1.1)
    - from C. H. Davis, 24 June 1853; (MS) (Folder 1.2)
    - from B. S. Hendrick, 1 June 1853; (MS) (Folder 1.3)
    - from B. S. Hendrick, 27 Apr 1853; (MS) (Folder 1.4)
    - from B. S. Hendrick, 15 July 1853; (MS) (Folder 1.5)
    - from B. S. Hendrick, 25 July 1853; (MS) (Folder 1.6)
    - from [Mary] A. Livermore, 20 Feb 1876; (MS) (Folder 1.6a)
    - from [James] [Edward] Oliver, 25 Nov 1871; (MS, TS) (Folder 1.7)
    - from J. H. R. [John H. Raymond], undated; (TS) (Folder 1.8)
    - from Arthur Searle, 7 Feb 1877; (MS) (Folder 1.9)
    - from Arthur Searle, 16 Mar 1877; (MS) (Folder 1.10)
    - from [Ellen] H. Swallow, 29 Nov 1872; (TS) (Folder 1.11)
    - from [James] [Monroe] Taylor, 9 Jan 1888; (MS, TS[draft?]) (Folder 1.12)
  - Letters from Maria Mitchell
    - to Elizabeth Owen Abbot, [circa 14 Feb 1874]; (MS) (Folder 1.13)
    - to Alvin Clark & Sons, 21 June 1887; (MS) (Folder 1.14)
    - to Rev. [E. G.?] Ames, [circa 5 Nov 1887]; (MS) (Folder 1.15)
    - to Dr. Rufus Babcock, 23 Oct 1862; (MS, TS) (Folder 1.16)
    - to Dr. Rufus Babcock, 18 Mar 1864; (MS, TS) (Folder 1.17)
    - to Dr. Rufus Babcock, undated; (MS, TS) (Folder 1.18)
    - to Rev. Bartol, 1 Dec 1873; (MS, TS) (Folder 1.19)
    - to President [Samuel L.] Caldwell, 13 May 1882; (TS) (Folder 1.20)
    - to Miss Caufield, 30 May 1886; (MS) (Folder 1.20)
    - to Professor [LeRoy C.] Cooley, undated; (MS, TS) (Folder 1.21)
    - to Miss Day, 25 June 1886; (MS, TS) (Folder 1.22)
    - to Dr. [William B.] Dwight, undated; (MS) (Folder 1.23)
    - to Miss Fletcher, undated; (TS) (Folder 1.23)
    - to President Folwell, 24 May 1880; (TS) (Folder 1.24)
    - to Mrs. Gibson, 29 May 1888; (Reprint) (Folder 1.24)
    - to Miss Hillhouse, 3 Aug [no year]; (MS, TS) (Folder 1.25)
    - to Mary A. Hopson, 26 Nov [1883]; (MS, TS) (Folder 1.26)
    - to Joseph N. Jackson, 17 Sept 1869; (MS, TS) (Folder 1.27)
    - to Kate, 4 Jan 1861; (MS, TS) (Folder 1.28)
    - to Dr. [J. Ryland] Kendrick, 15 Nov 1881; (MS) (Folder 1.29)
    - to Miss [Ella C.] Lapham, undated; (TS) (Folder 1.30)
    - to Mrs. [Mary] Livermore, 23 Aug [no year]; (MS, TS) (Folder 1.30)
    - to Mrs. Gay, [Sep 1854]; (MS) (Folder 1.31)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 13 Mar 1867; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.1)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 15 Mar 1867; (MS) (Folder 2.2)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 12 July 1868; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.3)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 4 Nov 1868; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.4)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 4 Nov 1868; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.5)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 13 July [1870?]; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.6)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 20 May 1871; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.7)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 8 June 1871; (MS) (Folder 2.8)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 3 Aug 1871; (TS) (Folder 2.8)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 10 Nov 1871; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.9)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 16 Dec 1871; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.10)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 9 May 1872; (2 MS, TS) (Folder 2.11)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 3 July [1872?]; (MS) (Folder 2.12)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 12 June 1875; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.13)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 12 June 1877; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.14)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 12 June 1879; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.15)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 30 May 1880; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.16)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 14 June 1880; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.17)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 2 Aug 1881; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.18)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 11 Aug 1881; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.19)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 16 Sept 1885; (MS) (Folder 2.20)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 25 Apr 1886; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.21)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, 6 June [no year]; (MS) (Folder 2.22)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, [20 June no year]; (TS) (Folder 2.22)
    - to Benson J. Lossing, undated; (7 MS, 7 TS) (Folder 2.23)
    - to Mrs. Benson J. Lossing, [circa 30 June no year]; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.24)
    - to [Ann] [Eliza] Morse, 12 Aug [1878?]; (MS) (Folder 2.25)
    - to A. E. Morse, 11 Oct [1880?]; (MS) (Folder 2.26)
    - to A. E. Morse, 16 Feb 1882; (MS, TS [fragment]) (Folder 2.27)
    - to A. E. Morse, [1887?]; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.28)
    - to A. E. Morse, 1 Jan [1888]; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.29)
    - to A. E. Morse, 24 March [no year]; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.30)
    - to A. E. Morse, 11 April [no year]; (MS, TS [fragment]) (Folder 2.31)
    - to A. E. Morse, [circa 26 April no year]; (MS, TS) (Folder 2.32)
    - to A. E. Moore, undated; (5 MS, 5 TS) (Folder 2.33)
    - to "My Dear Little Friends,", undated; (MS) (Folder 3.1)
    - to Isabel Nelson, [circa 12 May 1882]; (MS) (Folder 3.2)
    - to Edith Nicholson, undated; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.3)
    - to [Louise Parsons], 31 May [1870]; (TS) (Folder 3.4)
    - to Mrs. Patton, 26 February 1886; (MS) (Folder 3.4)
    - to Mrs. Patton, 21 July 1886; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.4)
    - to Cornelia Raymond[daughter of John H. Raymond], [circa 4 Mar 1885]; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.5)
    - to Cornelia Raymond, undated; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.6)
    - to John H. Raymond, 29 July 1867; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.7)
    - to John H. Raymond, 8 July 1868; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.8)
    - to John H. Raymond, 22 Aug 1868; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.9)
    - to John H. Raymond, 7 Dec 1868; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.10)
    - to John H. Raymond, 25 Apr 1869; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.11)
    - to John H. Raymond, 2 Oct 1869; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.12)
    - to John H. Raymond, 16 May 1870; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.13)
    - to John H. Raymond, 16 May 1870; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.14)
    - to John H. Raymond, [28 Feb 1871]; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.15)
    - to John H. Raymond, 5 Dec 1873; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.16)
    - to John H. Raymond, undated; (5 MS, 5 TS) (Folder 3.17)
    - to Mrs. John H. Raymond [Cornelia M. Raymond], [1878]; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.18)
    - to Mrs. John H. Raymond, 3 Aug 1881; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.19)
    - to Mrs. John H. Raymond, [10 Aug 1883]; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.20)
    - to Mrs. John H. Raymond, 26 Jan 1887; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.21)
    - to Mrs. John H. Raymond, [1889?]; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.22)
    - to Mrs. John H. Raymond, 12 January [no year]; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.23)
    - to Mrs. John H. Raymond, 19 August [1878-1883?]; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.24)
    - to Mrs. John H. Raymond, 12 December [no year]; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.25)
    - to Mrs. John H. Raymond, undated; (7 MS, 7 TS) (Folder 3.26)
    - to Mary [Carrington] Raymond, 20 Oct [no year]; (MS, TS) (Folder 3.27)
    - to Mary C. Raymond, 9 July [1878]; (TS) (Folder 3.27)
    - to Mary C. Raymond, undated; (4 TS) (Folder 3.27)
    - to Mary Carrington Raymond [later Richardson], 9 December 1868; (MS) (Folder 3.28)
    - to William James Richardson [son-in-law of Cornelia M. Raymond, wife of President Raymond], [Summer 1883]; (MS) (Folder 3.29)
    - to Miss Scott, 10 Mar 1880; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.1)
    - to Mary Scott, [July 1881]; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.2)
    - to Mary Scott, [6 Mar 1882]; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.3)
    - to Mary Scott, [circa 21 Nov no year]; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.4)
    - to Miss A. Scott, [circa 1 April no year]; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.5)
    - to Miss A. Scott, undated; (3 MS, TS) (Folder 4.6)
    - to Marion Scribner & Family, 23 Oct 1872; (MS) (Folder 4.7)
    - to Cyrus Swan, 19 Dec 1865; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.8)
    - to Cyrus Swan, [Jan 1866]; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.9)
    - to Cyrus Swan, [4 Apr 1866]; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.10)
    - to Cyrus Swan, 14 Aug 1866; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.11)
    - to Cyrus Swan, 28 Aug 1866; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.12)
    - to Cyrus Swan, 13 Nov [1871?]; (MS) (Folder 4.13)
    - to Cyrus Swan, [15 Nov 1871]; (MS) (Folder 4.14)
    - to Cyrus Swan, 26 Nov [1871?]; (MS) (Folder 4.15)
    - to Cyrus Swan, 14 Nov [no year]; (MS) (Folder 4.16)
    - to Frances Swan, 2 June [no year]; (MS) (Folder 4.17)
    - to Frances Swan, 10 July [no year]; (MS) (Folder 4.18)
    - to Frances Swan, undated; (2 MS) (Folder 4.19)
    - to Willie [Swan], undated; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.19)
    - to James Monroe Taylor, 8 Jan 1888; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.20)
    - to James Monroe Taylor, 15 Jan 1888; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.21)
    - to James Monroe Taylor, [June 1888]; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.22)
    - to James Monroe Taylor, 18 Oct [1888]; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.23)
    - to James Monroe Taylor, 17 Jan [1888]; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.24)
    - to Robert Taylor, [circa 15 Jan 1888]; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.25)
    - to John Thompson, undated; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.26)
    - to "Trustees of Vassar College..,", [24 June 1872]; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.27)
    - to Matthew Vassar, 22 Nov 1862; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.28)
    - to Miss [Mary] Whitney, [circa 11 Jan 1888]; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.29)
    - to Frances Wood, undated; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.30)
    - to Ida Wood, [circa 23 Oct 1886]; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.31)
    - to Ida Wood, [1888?]; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.32)
    - to Ida Wood, undated; (MS, TS) (Folder 4.32)
    - to Miss Wood, 12 Aug [1878?]; (TS) (Folder 4.33)
    - to unknown addressee, Feb 1874; (TS) (Folder 4.34)
    - Fragments, undated; (3 MS, 3 TS); Fragment "I send what I call a good view ..." includes hand- drawn diagram of Vassar College Observatory (Folder 4.35)
  - Letters about Maria Mitchell
    - [Rev.] [Rufus] Babcock to [Matthew] Vassar, 8 Sept 1862; (MS, TS) (Folder 5.1)
    - [Rev.] Rufus Babcock to [Matthew] Vassar, 10 Sept 1862; (MS, TS) (Folder 5.2)
    - George F. Barnard to Moses A. Cartland, 29 Apr 1849; (TS) (Folder 5.3)
    - Nathan Bishop to Dr. [Samuel L.] Caldwell, 1 Mar 1879; (MS, TS) (Folder 5.4)
    - Alexis Caswell to Rev. Dr. Babcock, 4 Sept 1862; (MS, TS) (Folder 5.5)
    - Charles Farrar to President [John H.] Raymond, 13 Feb 1865; (MS, TS) (Folder 5.6)
    - Martha LeB. Goddard to Mrs. Spaulding, 24 Sept 1875; (TS) (Folder 5.7)
    - Abby M. Goodwin to Miss [Mary] Whitney, 17 Dec 1887; 11 Jan 1888; (2 TS) (Folder 5.8)
    - Alice Hayes to Prof. Whitney, 28 May 1916; (TS) (Folder 5.9)
    - Phoebe Mitchell Kendall to [James Monroe] Taylor, 28 Oct 1889; (TS) (Folder 5.10)
    - Anne Mitchell Macy to Dr. [James Monroe] Taylor, 28 June 1889; (MS, TS) (Folder 5.11)
    - Anne Mitchell Macy to Dr. [James Monroe] Taylor, 27 July 1889; (MS, TS) (Folder 5.12)
    - [Ann Mitchell] Macy to President [James Monroe] Taylor, 29 June 1889; (MS, TS) (Folder 5.13)
    - Anne Mitchell Macy to Miss [Mary] Whitney, 21 Mar 1888; (TS) (Folder 5.14)
    - Frances M. Macy to Dr. [James Monroe] Taylor, 28 June 1889; (MS, TS) (Folder 5.15)
    - Henry Mitchell to President [James Monroe] Taylor, 29 June 1889; (MS, TS) (Folder 5.16)
    - Henry Mitchell to Prof. [Mary] Whitney, 21 Jan 1890; (MS, TS) (Folder 5.17)
    - Maria Mitchell & Alida Avery to Board of Trustees regarding terms of employment, undated; (TS) (Folder 5.18)
    - William Mitchell to Mary Carrington Raymond, 2 Oct 1868; (TS) (Folder 5.19)
    - William Mitchell to Mary Carrington Raymond, 15 Jan 1869; (MS) (Folder 5.19)
    - William Mitchell to[Maria Louise Booth], 21 Nov 1868; (MS, TS) (Folder 5.20)
    - Benjamin Pierce to Dr. Babcock, 30 Aug 1862; (MS, TS) (Folder 5.21)
    - [John] H. Raymond to President Magill, 15 June 1874; (MS, TS) (Folder 5.22)
    - [Mary C. Raymond] to Nell [Cornelia Raymond], 1 Feb [1885]; (TS) (Folder 5.23)
    - [Cyrus] Swan to [James Monroe] Taylor, 11 Jan 1888; (MS, TS) (Folder 5.24)
    - [James] [Monroe] Taylor to Miss [Mary] Whitney, 11 Jan 1888; (TS) (Folder 5.25)
    - [Mary] W. Whitney to Dr. [James Monroe] Taylor, undated; (MS, TS) (Folder 5.26)
    - Correspondence re: Dassel & Humbolt paintings, 1889-1940 (Folder 5.27)
  - Correspondence about Maria Mitchell As Her Students Knew Her
    - Mary King Babbitt re: Maria Mitchell As Her Students Knew Her, 1912-1915 (Folder 5.28)
    - Mary King Babbitt re: Maria Mitchell As Her Students Knew Her, undated (Folder 5.29)
  - Correspondence about Sweeper in the Sky
    - Helen Wright re: Sweeper in the Sky, 1939-1940 (Folder 5.30)
    - Helen Wright re: Sweeper in the Sky, 1946-undated (Folder 5.31)
- SERIES II. VASSAR COLLEGE ASTRONOMY DEPARTMENT, 1871-1886
  - Department Reports: Notes for 1871-1886, undated (Folder 6.1)
  - List of donations of books to the V. C. Observatory, undated (Folder 6.2)
  - Astronomical Classes at V. C. Observatory, undated (Folder 6.3)
  - Student(?) notes on reversing of transit instruments, undated (Folder 6.4)
  - Student(?) paper with drawings, undated (Folder 6.5)
  - Astronomical photographs, undated (Folder 6.6)
- SERIES III. MARIA MITCHELL'S DOME PARTIES, 1870
  - First Dome Party, 1870 (Folder 6.7)
  - Dome Party: Verses, undated (Folder 6.8)
  - Dome Party: Verses, undated (Folder 6.9)
  - Dome Party: Verses, undated (Folder 6.10)
  - Dome Party: Verses, undated (Folder 6.11)
- SERIES IV. MITCHELL NOTES, LECTURE NOTES, AND NOTEBOOKS, 1843-1893
  - Notes and Lecture Notes
    - Comet of 1881, undated (Folder 6.12)
    - Eclipse for 1885, undated (Folder 6.13)
    - Lecture notes: "Periods of Nature,", undated (Folder 6.14)
    - Lecture notes: "The Sun Dial,", undated (Folder 6.15)
    - Lecture notes on astronomical attraction, undated (Folder 6.16)
    - Miscellaneous fragments, undated (Folder 6.17)
    - "My Dear Little Nellie" [ms. poem by Mitchell written for Cornelia Raymond, President John Raymond's daughter], undated (Folder 6.18)
    - Astronomical drawings, undated (Folder 6.19)
  - Notebooks and Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings on comets, 1843-1882 (Folder 7.1)
    - Notebook, undated (Folder 7.2)
    - Notebook: Book of questions, undated (Folder 7.3)
    - Notebook: Lectures [by Benjamin Peirce] on Quaternions, 1869-1870 (Folder 7.4)
    - Notebook: Observing -- rough notes, May 1884 - Jan 1885 (Folder 7.5)
    - Notebook: Rough records of Observatory, Oct 1885 - Feb 1886 (Folder 7.6)
    - Notebook: Observatory rough work, some Jupiter, 1885 (Folder 7.7)
    - Notebook: Rough work, Feb 1886 (Folder 7.8)
    - Notebook: Observatory, Sep 1886 - Feb 1887 (Folder 7.9)
    - Notebook: 1st rough observations with Equatoreal, 1865-1866 (Folder 8.1)
    - Notebook: Rough work, Recomputing of Decs. of zenith stars, no. 1, undated (Folder 8.2)
    - Notebook: Rough work, Recomputing of zenith stars, no. 2, undated (Folder 8.3)
    - Notebook: Rough work, [zenith?] stars, no. 3, [1872-1873] (Folder 8.4)
    - Notebook: Recomputing of zenith disks, no. 4, undated (Folder 8.5)
    - Notebook: Longitude computations of occultations, 1872-1875 (Folder 8.6)
    - Notebook: Sun, meteors and other phenomena, (including remarkable meteoric evening of 27 November 1872), 1870-1873 (Folder 8.7)
    - Notebook: Observations of class of 1866-67 and 1867-68, undated (Folder 8.8)
    - Notebook: Student observations, 22 Mar - 31 Oct 1866; Meteors, 12 Nov 1867 (Folder 8.9)
    - Notebook: Astronomical observations of the Advanced class, 1868-1869 (Folder 8.10)
    - Notebook: Observations of class of 1868-69, no. 2 (Folder 8.11)
    - Notebook: Class observations for time, 1872 (Folder 9.1)
    - Notebook: Sun, meteors, etc.; Risings and settings of planets, etc.; Miss Kellogg's record of August meteors, 1873-1874 (Folder 9.2)
    - Notebook: Anna Mineah [student] (Folder 9.3)
    - Notebook: S. C. Blatchley [student?] observations, 1866 (Folder 9.4)
    - Notebook: Observatory, Saturn, Sep 1877 - Jan 1878 (Folder 9.5)
    - Notebook: Meteors, students' notes, sun spots, 1875-1876 (Folder 9.6)
    - Notebook: Meteors and students' notes, Nov 1876 (Folder 9.7)
    - Notebook: variable stars, 1896- (Folder 9.7)
    - Notebook: Class rough records, May, Sep and Nov 1886 (Folder 9.8)
    - Notebook: Observations with the twelve-inch equatorial, 13 April 1866 - 17 June 1877 (Folder 10.1)
    - Notebook: twelve-inch equatorial, 28 Sep 1876 - 19 Oct 1879 (Folder 10.2)
    - Notebook: twelve-inch equatorial, 25 Oct 1879 - 31 May 1886 (Folder 10.3)
    - Notebook: Observations for time and for longitude; transit instrument, 22 Sep 1865 - 6 Dec 1871 (Folder 11.1)
    - Notebook: Transit instrument, 5 May 1878 - 8 Dec 1887 (Folder 11.2)
    - Notebook: Observations with meridian instrument and zenith telescope, undated (Folder 11.3)
    - Notebook: Washington and Cambridge, record of time signals received from Washington, undated (Folder 12.1)
    - Notebook: Longitude, Cambridge and Vassar, undated (Folder 12.2)
    - Notebook: Venus transit, 6 Dec 1882 (Folder 12.3)